<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Schemescape</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/</id>
<link rel="self" href="https://log.schemescape.com/feed.xml"/>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/"/>
<author>
<name>Schemescape</name>
</author>
<updated>2021-11-05T21:03:25.284Z</updated>

<entry>
<title>NPM requires X11 on Debian. Wait, what?</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/posts/linux/debian-npm-requires-x11.html</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/posts/linux/debian-npm-requires-x11.html"/>
<updated>2021-11-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<summary type="text">Here&#x27;s a rant about that time I tried to install NPM on Debian.</summary>
<content type="html">&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;debian&quot;&gt;Debian&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://www.debian.org/&quot;&gt;Debian&lt;/a&gt; has been my preferred Linux distribution for a long time (longer than &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://ubuntu.com/&quot;&gt;Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt; has even existed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main reason I like Debian is that its &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://manpages.debian.org/buster/apt/apt.8.en.html&quot;&gt;apt&lt;/a&gt; package manager has been the most reliable package manager I&amp;#39;ve ever dealt with, especially when it comes to removing and/or upgrading packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;npm&quot;&gt;NPM&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I&amp;#39;ve been playing around with Node and NPM on Windows, I decided I should see if one of my tools works on Linux. Fortunately, I was on Debian 11, which ships with a not-&lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt;-out-of-date Node v12 runtime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great, I&amp;#39;ll just run &lt;code&gt;sudo apt install nodejs npm&lt;/code&gt; and get started! I was immediately greeted with the following wall of packages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-txt&quot;&gt;$ sudo apt install nodejs npm
Reading package lists... Done
Building dependency tree... Done
Reading state information... Done
The following additional packages will be installed:
  at-spi2-core dbus-user-session dconf-gsettings-backend dconf-service glib-networking glib-networking-common glib-networking-services gsettings-desktop-schemas gyp javascript-common libatk-bridge2.0-0 libatspi2.0-0 libauthen-sasl-perl
  libc-ares2 libclone-perl libcolord2 libdata-dump-perl libdconf1 libdrm-amdgpu1 libdrm-common libdrm-intel1 libdrm-nouveau2 libdrm-radeon1 libdrm2 libencode-locale-perl libepoxy0 libfile-basedir-perl libfile-desktopentry-perl
  libfile-listing-perl libfile-mimeinfo-perl libfont-afm-perl libfontenc1 libgl1 libgl1-mesa-dri libglapi-mesa libglvnd0 libglx-mesa0 libglx0 libgtk-3-0 libgtk-3-bin libgtk-3-common libhtml-form-perl libhtml-format-perl
  libhtml-parser-perl libhtml-tagset-perl libhtml-tree-perl libhttp-cookies-perl libhttp-daemon-perl libhttp-date-perl libhttp-message-perl libhttp-negotiate-perl libice6 libio-html-perl libio-socket-ssl-perl libio-stringy-perl
  libipc-system-simple-perl libjs-highlight.js libjs-inherits libjs-is-typedarray libjs-psl libjs-typedarray-to-buffer libjson-glib-1.0-0 libjson-glib-1.0-common liblcms2-2 libllvm11 liblua5.3-0 liblwp-mediatypes-perl
  liblwp-protocol-https-perl libmailtools-perl libnet-dbus-perl libnet-http-perl libnet-smtp-ssl-perl libnet-ssleay-perl libnode-dev libnode72 libpciaccess0 libproxy1v5 librest-0.7-0 libsensors-config libsensors5 libsm6
  libsoup-gnome2.4-1 libsoup2.4-1 libssl-dev libtie-ixhash-perl libtimedate-perl libtry-tiny-perl liburi-perl libuv1 libuv1-dev libvte-2.91-0 libvte-2.91-common libvulkan1 libwayland-client0 libwayland-cursor0 libwayland-egl1
  libwww-perl libwww-robotrules-perl libx11-protocol-perl libx11-xcb1 libxaw7 libxcb-dri2-0 libxcb-dri3-0 libxcb-glx0 libxcb-present0 libxcb-randr0 libxcb-shape0 libxcb-sync1 libxcb-xfixes0 libxft2 libxkbcommon0 libxkbfile1
  libxml-parser-perl libxml-twig-perl libxml-xpathengine-perl libxmu6 libxshmfence1 libxt6 libxtst6 libxv1 libxxf86dga1 libxxf86vm1 libz3-4 mesa-vulkan-drivers node-abbrev node-agent-base node-ajv node-ansi node-ansi-regex
  node-ansi-styles node-ansistyles node-aproba node-archy node-are-we-there-yet node-asap node-asn1 node-assert-plus node-asynckit node-aws-sign2 node-aws4 node-balanced-match node-bcrypt-pbkdf node-brace-expansion node-builtins
  node-cacache node-caseless node-chalk node-chownr node-clone node-color-convert node-color-name node-colors node-columnify node-combined-stream node-concat-map node-console-control-strings node-copy-concurrently node-core-util-is
  node-dashdash node-debug node-defaults node-delayed-stream node-delegates node-depd node-ecc-jsbn node-encoding node-err-code node-escape-string-regexp node-extend node-extsprintf node-fast-deep-equal node-forever-agent
  node-form-data node-fs-write-stream-atomic node-fs.realpath node-function-bind node-gauge node-getpass node-glob node-graceful-fs node-gyp node-har-schema node-har-validator node-has-flag node-has-unicode node-hosted-git-info
  node-http-signature node-https-proxy-agent node-iconv-lite node-iferr node-imurmurhash node-indent-string node-inflight node-inherits node-ini node-ip node-ip-regex node-is-typedarray node-isarray node-isexe node-isstream node-jsbn
  node-json-parse-better-errors node-json-schema node-json-schema-traverse node-json-stable-stringify node-json-stringify-safe node-jsonify node-jsonparse node-jsonstream node-jsprim node-leven node-lockfile node-lru-cache node-mime
  node-mime-types node-minimatch node-mkdirp node-move-concurrently node-ms node-mute-stream node-nopt node-normalize-package-data node-npm-bundled node-npm-package-arg node-npmlog node-number-is-nan node-oauth-sign node-object-assign
  node-once node-opener node-osenv node-p-map node-path-is-absolute node-performance-now node-process-nextick-args node-promise-inflight node-promise-retry node-promzard node-psl node-puka node-punycode node-qs node-read
  node-read-package-json node-readable-stream node-request node-resolve node-resolve-from node-retry node-rimraf node-run-queue node-safe-buffer node-semver node-set-blocking node-signal-exit node-slash node-spdx-correct
  node-spdx-exceptions node-spdx-expression-parse node-spdx-license-ids node-sshpk node-ssri node-string-decoder node-string-width node-strip-ansi node-supports-color node-tar node-text-table node-through node-tough-cookie
  node-tunnel-agent node-tweetnacl node-typedarray-to-buffer node-unique-filename node-universalify node-uri-js node-util-deprecate node-uuid node-validate-npm-package-license node-validate-npm-package-name node-verror node-wcwidth.js
  node-which node-wide-align node-wrappy node-write-file-atomic node-yallist nodejs-doc perl-openssl-defaults python3-pkg-resources termit x11-common x11-utils x11-xserver-utils xdg-utils xkb-data
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#39;s a lot more packages than I was expecting. Wait, &lt;code&gt;x11-common&lt;/code&gt;? &lt;code&gt;x11-xserver-utils&lt;/code&gt;? What&amp;#39;s going on here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://packages.debian.org/bullseye/npm&quot;&gt;Debian&amp;#39;s package for NPM&lt;/a&gt; depends on something called &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://packages.debian.org/bullseye/node-opener&quot;&gt;node-opener&lt;/a&gt;, which depends on &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://packages.debian.org/bullseye/xdg-utils&quot;&gt;xdg-utils&lt;/a&gt;, which is described as &amp;quot;desktop integration utilities from freedesktop.org&amp;quot;. Uh oh. Yeah, that depends on X11.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why in the world does a command line package manager depend on a GUI environment?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;node-opener&quot;&gt;node-opener&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what is this &lt;code&gt;node-opener&lt;/code&gt; thing, and does NPM really require it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/domenic/opener&quot;&gt;package&amp;#39;s web site&lt;/a&gt; describes it as &amp;quot;Opens stuff, like webpages and files and executables, cross-platform&amp;quot;. I&amp;#39;m still not seeing the relation to NPM. Looking at the code, it&amp;#39;s just a script that calls &lt;code&gt;xdg-open&lt;/code&gt; on Linux (and other commands on Windows and Mac).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/npm/cli/blob/04eb43f2b2a387987b61a7318908cf18f03d97e0/lib/utils/open-url.js&quot;&gt;Peering into NPM&amp;#39;s source code&lt;/a&gt;, I see that it does in fact seem to &lt;code&gt;require(&amp;#39;opener&amp;#39;)&lt;/code&gt;. That&amp;#39;s disappointing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;nodesource-to-the-rescue&quot;&gt;NodeSource to the rescue?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official nodejs.org site &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://nodejs.org/en/download/package-manager/#debian-and-ubuntu-based-linux-distributions&quot;&gt;mentions&lt;/a&gt; binary distributions &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/nodesource/distributions/blob/master/README.md&quot;&gt;from NodeSource&lt;/a&gt;. NodeSource helpfully suggests downloading and running their setup script as root.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The script appears to mostly do reasonable things like checking for required packages and then updating apt&amp;#39;s &lt;code&gt;sources.list&lt;/code&gt; file, and I guess I&amp;#39;m trusting them with the binaries they&amp;#39;re providing, so I&amp;#39;ll give it a try. They do provide manual install instructions as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;success&quot;&gt;Success&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;#39;t say I&amp;#39;m pleased with this setup, but NodeSource&amp;#39;s Node package did in fact work and now I&amp;#39;ve got &lt;code&gt;node&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;npm&lt;/code&gt; commands running fine without an X11 installation.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Embedding VS Code&#x27;s Monaco Editor using a CDN</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/posts/web-development/embedding-monaco-from-cdn.html</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/posts/web-development/embedding-monaco-from-cdn.html"/>
<updated>2021-11-02T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<summary type="text">Here&#x27;s how to load VS Code&#x27;s Monaco Editor from a CDN and embed it in a static web page, with automatic resizing.</summary>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s how to load Visual Studio Code&amp;#39;s Monaco Editor from a CDN and embed it in a static web page, with automatic resizing of the editor component:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/monaco-editor-from-cdn&quot;&gt;Source code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://jaredkrinke.github.io/monaco-editor-from-cdn/&quot;&gt;Live demo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;monaco-editor&quot;&gt;Monaco Editor&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://code.visualstudio.com/&quot;&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/a&gt; unseated &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://www.vim.org/&quot;&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt; as my favorite text editor a few years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, VS Code manages to have acceptable performance (even on my very old laptop) despite being built on JavaScript. The (MIT-licensed) editor component is called &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://microsoft.github.io/monaco-editor/index.html&quot;&gt;Monaco Editor&lt;/a&gt;, and it runs in most desktop browsers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;samples&quot;&gt;Samples&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what&amp;#39;s the easiest way to embed Monaco Editor in a web page for building simple tools?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s an official repository for &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/Microsoft/monaco-editor-samples/&quot;&gt;Monaco Editor samples&lt;/a&gt;, but they all seem to assume you&amp;#39;re using NPM, WebPack, etc., and hosting the scripts yourself. &lt;strong&gt;What if you just want to throw together a quick web page with an editor component, hosted as a single static HTML page?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;loading-from-a-cdn&quot;&gt;Loading from a CDN&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there is a (very well hidden) page discussing &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/microsoft/monaco-editor/blob/main/docs/integrate-amd-cross.md&quot;&gt;integrating the AMD version of the Monaco Editor in a cross-domain setup&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are hosting your .js on a different domain &lt;strong&gt;(e.g. on a CDN)&lt;/strong&gt; than the HTML, you should know that the Monaco Editor creates web workers for smart language features. Cross-domain web workers are not allowed, but here is how you can proxy their loading and get them to work&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That sounds like what I&amp;#39;m looking for!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specifically, I&amp;#39;m going to combine one of the &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/microsoft/monaco-editor-samples/blob/main/browser-amd-editor/index.html&quot;&gt;browser-amd-editor&lt;/a&gt; official samples with &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/microsoft/monaco-editor-samples/blob/main/browser-amd-editor/index.html&quot;&gt;Option 1&lt;/a&gt; from the page above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;automatic-resizing&quot;&gt;Automatic resizing&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s one line in the sample I find irritating:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div id&#x3D;&amp;quot;container&amp;quot; style&#x3D;&amp;quot;width: 800px; height: 600px; border: 1px solid grey&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is the size being manually specified in pixels?&lt;/strong&gt; Is that necessary?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s a &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/Microsoft/monaco-editor/issues/28&quot;&gt;long thread in a Monaco Editor issue&lt;/a&gt; that goes into the details, but basically the editor component needs to be notified of size changes (no idea why) and, at least in 2016, there was no way for the editor to subscribe to size updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;#39;s 2021 as of this post, so can we use &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/ResizeObserver&quot;&gt;ResizeObserver&lt;/a&gt; (global support is at &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://caniuse.com/resizeobserver&quot;&gt;92%&lt;/a&gt; as of this post)? Apparently not, because the implementations of ResizeObserver use inconsistent property names (insert facepalm here).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, the trusty old &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Window/resize_event&quot;&gt;resize&lt;/a&gt; event is sufficient for my purposes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;const editorElement &#x3D; document.getElementById(&amp;quot;editor&amp;quot;);
window.addEventListener(&amp;quot;resize&amp;quot;, () &#x3D;&amp;gt; editor.layout({
    width: editorElement.offsetWidth,
    height: editorElement.offsetHeight
}));
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;complete-example&quot;&gt;Complete example&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full code is in this repository: &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/monaco-editor-from-cdn&quot;&gt;monaco-editor-from-cdn&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s a &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://jaredkrinke.github.io/monaco-editor-from-cdn/&quot;&gt;live demo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s a copy-paste of the code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-html&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;!DOCTYPE html&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;html lang&#x3D;&amp;quot;en&amp;quot;&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;head&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;meta charset&#x3D;&amp;quot;utf-8&amp;quot; /&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;Monaco Editor from CDN example, with automatic resizing&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;style&amp;gt;
/* Flex column layout, with the editor taking up all available screen space */
html, body {
    height: 100%;
    margin: 0;
    overflow: hidden;
}

body {
    display: flex;
    flex-direction: column;
}

#editor {
    flex-grow: 1;
    border: solid 1px gray;
    overflow: hidden;
}
&amp;lt;/style&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;h1&amp;gt;Monaco Editor, loaded via CDN&amp;lt;/h1&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;div id&#x3D;&amp;quot;editor&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;script src&#x3D;&amp;quot;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/monaco-editor/0.29.1/min/vs/loader.min.js&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;script&amp;gt;
// Proxy Monaco Editor workers using a data URL (adapted from: https://github.com/microsoft/monaco-editor/blob/main/docs/integrate-amd-cross.md)
require.config({ paths: { &amp;quot;vs&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/monaco-editor/0.29.1/min/vs/&amp;quot; }});

window.MonacoEnvironment &#x3D; {
    getWorkerUrl: function(workerId, label) {
        return &#x60;data:text/javascript;charset&#x3D;utf-8,${encodeURIComponent(&#x60;
            self.MonacoEnvironment &#x3D; { baseUrl: &amp;quot;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/monaco-editor/0.29.1/min/&amp;quot; };
            importScripts(&amp;quot;https://cdnjs.cloudflare.com/ajax/libs/monaco-editor/0.29.1/min/vs/base/worker/workerMain.min.js&amp;quot;);&#x60;
        )}&#x60;;
    }
};

require([&amp;quot;vs/editor/editor.main&amp;quot;], function () {
    // Create the editor with some sample JavaScript code
    var editor &#x3D; monaco.editor.create(document.getElementById(&amp;quot;editor&amp;quot;), {
        value: &amp;quot;// code goes here\n&amp;quot;,
        language: &amp;quot;javascript&amp;quot;
    });

    // Resize the editor when the window size changes
    const editorElement &#x3D; document.getElementById(&amp;quot;editor&amp;quot;);
    window.addEventListener(&amp;quot;resize&amp;quot;, () &#x3D;&amp;gt; editor.layout({
        width: editorElement.offsetWidth,
        height: editorElement.offsetHeight
    }));
});
&amp;lt;/script&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Designing md2blog, a zero-config static site generator for dev blogs</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/md2blog-design.html</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/md2blog-design.html"/>
<updated>2021-10-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<summary type="text">Here&#x27;s the design of my in-progress static site generator, md2blog.</summary>
<content type="html">&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/comparison.html&quot;&gt;investigating many popular static site generators&lt;/a&gt;, I wasn&amp;#39;t able to find a convenient static site generator that met my needs out of the box. Fortunately, I was able to leverage &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://metalsmith.io/&quot;&gt;Metalsmith&lt;/a&gt; (and numerous plugins) to get what I wanted. I&amp;#39;m calling the resulting tool &lt;strong&gt;md2blog&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I&amp;#39;m going to cover the design of md2blog. Note that md2blog is a work in progress that has not been released yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;design-goals&quot;&gt;Design goals&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s the overarching goal of md2blog:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Convert a &lt;em&gt;self-contained, organized&lt;/em&gt; pile of &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; posts into a &lt;em&gt;minimal, but fully functional&lt;/em&gt; static blog, requiring &lt;em&gt;zero configuration&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key differentiator for md2blog is the &amp;quot;self-contained, organized&amp;quot; part. By this, I mean:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relative links between Markdown files (including anchors) &amp;quot;just work&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt; (and are validated at build time)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Source Markdown files &lt;strong&gt;can be viewed (with links and images) in any Markdown previewer&lt;/strong&gt; (e.g. VS Code or GitHub)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Posts are &lt;strong&gt;implicitly categorized based on directory structure&lt;/strong&gt; (supplemental tags are also supported)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the produced site is &amp;quot;minimal, but fully functional&amp;quot; in the following sense:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page templates use &lt;strong&gt;clean, semantic HTML&lt;/strong&gt; with only a few kilobytes of CSS (and no JavaScript)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relative links are used wherever possible&lt;/strong&gt;, so the site can be hosted anywhere (or even viewed directly from the file system)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Syntax highlighting&lt;/strong&gt; is automatically added to code blocks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/atom.html&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt;/RSS news feed is automatically generated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that &amp;quot;zero configuration&amp;quot; implies that md2blog is highly opinionated, to the point that there are no options to configure. &lt;strong&gt;Instead of fiddling with options and themes, the user&amp;#39;s focus is strictly on writing and publishing content.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;input&quot;&gt;Input&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s a more detailed look at building a dev blog with md2blog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id&#x3D;&quot;directory-structure&quot;&gt;Directory structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;content/&lt;/code&gt;: Root directory that contains all source content for the site&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;site.json&lt;/code&gt;: Site-wide metadata&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;assets/&lt;/code&gt;: Directory for assets (e.g. images)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;posts/&lt;/code&gt;: Directory for all posts&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;category1/&lt;/code&gt;: Directory for posts related to &amp;quot;category1&amp;quot;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;post1.md&lt;/code&gt;: Post related to &amp;quot;category1&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;post2.md&lt;/code&gt;: Another &amp;quot;category1&amp;quot; post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;category2/&lt;/code&gt;: Another category&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;post3.md&lt;/code&gt;: &amp;quot;category2&amp;quot; post&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id&#x3D;&quot;sitejson&quot;&gt;site.json&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s an example &lt;code&gt;site.json&lt;/code&gt; file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-json&quot;&gt;{
    &amp;quot;title&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;My dev blog&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;url&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;https://mydevblog.com/&amp;quot;,
    &amp;quot;description&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;A very good dev blog indeed&amp;quot;
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schema:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Field&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Required?&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Note&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;title&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;string&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Required&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;url&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;string&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Recommended&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Must end with &amp;quot;/&amp;quot;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;description&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;string&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Optional&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the site &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; generally work without specifying a URL, but the Atom feed will be forced to use relative links instead of absolute URLs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id&#x3D;&quot;posts&quot;&gt;Posts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posts are written in Markdown and use YAML for front matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id&#x3D;&quot;front-matter&quot;&gt;Front matter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s an example showing all of the supported YAML front matter properties (&lt;code&gt;keywords&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;draft&lt;/code&gt; are optional, the rest are required):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-yaml&quot;&gt;---
title: First post
description: First post on my blog, with a relative link.
date: 2021-10-26
keywords: [additional-tag]
draft: true
---
(Markdown content follows...)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schema:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Field&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Type&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Required?&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Note&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;title&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;string&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Required&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;description&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;string&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Required&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;This text is displayed on index pages&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;date&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;YYYY-MM-DD&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Required&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;keywords&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;string[]&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Optional&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Additional tags for categorizing the post&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;code&gt;draft&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Boolean&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Optional&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;If &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;, the post will only be built when serving locally&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;h3 id&#x3D;&quot;content&quot;&gt;Content&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s example Markdown content, demonstrating relative links (these links get translated to the corresponding HTML files and checked at build time; they also work in VS Code&amp;#39;s and GitHub&amp;#39;s Markdown previewers):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-markdown&quot;&gt;# Relative links
Here&amp;#39;s a relative link to another post in this category: [link](post2.md)!

And here&amp;#39;s one to another category, with an anchor: [link 2](../category2/post3.md#some-section).

# Image
Here&amp;#39;s an image:
![test](../../assets/test.png)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, here is an example of including a code block (specifying the language is recommended, but optional):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-markdown&quot;&gt;# Code block
Here&amp;#39;s some code:

&#x60;&#x60;&#x60;javascript
const add &#x3D; (a, b) &#x3D;&amp;gt; a + b;
&#x60;&#x60;&#x60;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;output&quot;&gt;Output&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All output is written to the &lt;code&gt;out/&lt;/code&gt; directory. Here&amp;#39;s what the output might look like for the example above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt;: Home page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;404.html&lt;/code&gt;: Error page&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;feed.xml&lt;/code&gt;: Atom news feed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;posts/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt;: Archive page containing links to all posts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;category1/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt;: Index page for &amp;quot;category1&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;post1.html&lt;/code&gt;: Post 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;post2.html&lt;/code&gt;: Post 2&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;category2/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt;: Index page for &amp;quot;category2&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;post3.html&lt;/code&gt;: Post 3&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;assets/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;test.png&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;css/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;style.css&lt;/code&gt;: CSS stylesheet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As noted previously, the entire site can viewed directly from the file system (no web server required).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Metalsmith&#x27;s downsides</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/metalsmith-downsides.html</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/metalsmith-downsides.html"/>
<updated>2021-10-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<summary type="text">I&#x27;m using Metalsmith to generate this site and, while I generally like it, it&#x27;s not perfect. Here are some of Metalsmith&#x27;s downsides.</summary>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/comparison.html&quot;&gt;testing out a bunch of static site generators&lt;/a&gt;, I settled on using &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/metalsmith.html&quot;&gt;Metalsmith&lt;/a&gt; for this site. I like that Metalsmith has a simple design that can be easily extended with plugins (either custom or &amp;quot;off the shelf&amp;quot;), but that&amp;#39;s not to say that Metalsmith is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s dive into the downsides of Metalsmith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;is-metalsmith-being-maintained&quot;&gt;Is Metalsmith being maintained?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#39;s the question of ownership and maintenance. Metalsmith was created by &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://segment.com/&quot;&gt;Segment&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/segmentio/metalsmith&quot;&gt;main repository&lt;/a&gt; lives under their GitHub account. Maintenance duties were &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/segmentio/metalsmith/pull/324/files&quot;&gt;transferred in 2018&lt;/a&gt;, but there have been no nontrivial commits since then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A pessimistic view is that Metalsmith is a zombie project.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s possible that Metalsmith is simple enough that it doesn&amp;#39;t &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; any updates, but if you do run into a problem with Metalsmith itself, you&amp;#39;re probably going to have to fix it yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, to me, is probably the biggest downside of building on top of Metalsmith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;are-the-plugins-being-maintained&quot;&gt;Are the plugins being maintained?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take the optimistic view that Metalsmith&amp;#39;s core is rock-solid and not in need of updates, how about the plugins? In many cases, &lt;strong&gt;plugins also appear to be unmaintained&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, take the &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/segmentio/metalsmith-collections&quot;&gt;metalsmith-collections&lt;/a&gt; plugin. Its last commit was 3 years ago, but even worse, the &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/segmentio/metalsmith-collections&quot;&gt;associated NPM package&lt;/a&gt; was published 5 years ago. In fact, the published package &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/segmentio/metalsmith-collections/issues/91&quot;&gt;doesn&amp;#39;t even contain the most up-to-date version of the plugin&lt;/a&gt;. I ran into this particular issue because I wanted to use the plugin&amp;#39;s &lt;code&gt;filterBy&lt;/code&gt; option, but that functionality isn&amp;#39;t actually present in the NPM package&amp;#39;s version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is unfortunate, but there&amp;#39;s nothing stopping you from forking and updating plugins yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;official-forum-sign-up-requirements&quot;&gt;Official forum sign-up requirements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://metalsmith.io/&quot;&gt;Metalsmith&amp;#39;s home page&lt;/a&gt; points to a &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://gitter.im/&quot;&gt;Gitter&lt;/a&gt; community, which I interpret to be the official forum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I like the &lt;em&gt;idea&lt;/em&gt; of an open source Discord alternative, I was very disappointed with my first experience using (well, attemping to use) Gitter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gitter was originally created as a way to chat about GitHub projects, so it was naturally tied to GitHub accounts. This was fine then, but even today Gitter requires one of the following accounts for login:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitLab&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use GitHub and have a high opinion of both it and GitLab (Twitter, not so much). But Gitter&amp;#39;s &lt;em&gt;default, required&lt;/em&gt; access requests are repulsive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub: &amp;quot;This application will be able to read your ... private project boards.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitLab: &amp;quot;Grants complete read/write access ... including all groups and projects ...&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Twitter: Requires a phone number to sign up (that I assume Twitter turns around and sells to advertisers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I already used Twitter, that would be an acceptable option here, but I have no interest in donating my personal data to yet another gigantic advertising company. Without a Twitter account, none of the login options seem even remotely reasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I created a dummy GitHub account just to access Gitter (which essentially negates any user benefit of using OAuth).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;plugin-ordering-and-lack-of-history&quot;&gt;Plugin ordering and lack of history&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite aspect of Metalsmith is its minimal design that can be easily extended with simple plugins, but I think the design is perhaps &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; minimal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Internally, Metalsmith manages a mapping of files to properties, and this mapping is handed from one plugin to the next, sequentially (and asynchronously). Each plugin &lt;em&gt;mutates&lt;/em&gt; the mapping however it wants, and eventually Metalsmith&amp;#39;s &lt;code&gt;build()&lt;/code&gt; function writes out the resulting files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is indeed a very simple design, but there is a subtle problem lurking: since each plugin can do whatever it wants, information can be changed or lost along the chain. This leads to numerous problems. Here are some examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/segmentio/metalsmith-markdown&quot;&gt;metalsmith-markdown&lt;/a&gt; renames files from &amp;quot;page.md&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;page.html&amp;quot;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subsequent plugins can no longer distinguish which HTML files were generated from Markdown and which were just static HTML files&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This makes supporting relative links (e.g. &lt;code&gt;./other-page.md&lt;/code&gt;) fragile (e.g. &lt;code&gt;./static-page.html&lt;/code&gt;, referring to a static HTML page--not generated using Markdown--is ambiguous)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/segmentio/metalsmith-permalinks&quot;&gt;metalsmith-permalinks&lt;/a&gt; moves files into different directories&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This plugin has to come before &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/radiovisual/metalsmith-rootpath&quot;&gt;metalsmith-rootpath&lt;/a&gt; to correctly construct a &amp;quot;relative path to root&amp;quot; property&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replacing paths also makes it essentially impossible to unambiguously link a source file to its destination, without adding additional plugins to the chain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current behavior is simple to reason over, and can be solved without changing the architecture (using more plugins!), but it is initially surprising, and certainly makes the tool harder to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;configuring-markdown&quot;&gt;Configuring Markdown&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One less prominent challenge with Metalsmith&amp;#39;s architecture is that there is no mechanism (or convention) for communicating between plugins. Probably an uncommon scenario, but it would be nice to allow plugins to configure Metalsmith&amp;#39;s Markdown options (without having to use an entirely separate Markdown plugin).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;so-do-i-hate-metalsmith-no&quot;&gt;So do I hate Metalsmith? No!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, this article makes a compelling case for avoiding Metalsmith--yet, I still use it. Why?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone who&amp;#39;s familiar with JavaScript, Node, and HTML/CSS, Metalsmith is simply the easiest static site generator for me to use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#39;s simple enough that I know exactly what it&amp;#39;s doing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It&amp;#39;s easy to customize and extend&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple plugins already exist for most of the things I want to do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It supports &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/jstransformers&quot;&gt;pretty much any template language&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I can even debug it, just by hitting F5 in VS Code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Metalsmith is really giving me the best of both using a pre-built static site generator and creating my own. It&amp;#39;s possible that the lack of maintenance will force me to switch to something else eventually, but for now I&amp;#39;m happy with it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Generating SVG diagrams automatically with Metalsmith</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/metalsmith-diagrams.html</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/metalsmith-diagrams.html"/>
<updated>2021-10-10T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<summary type="text">Metalsmith is used to build this static site. Here&#x27;s how Graphviz was integrated to automatically generate diagrams.</summary>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Now that I&amp;#39;ve &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/../webassembly/compiling-graphviz-to-webassembly.html&quot;&gt;compiled Graphviz to a WebAssembly module&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#39;m going to use it to automatically generate SVG diagrams when I build my static site using Metalsmith.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;the-plan&quot;&gt;The plan&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#39;s a flow chart of my general plan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;svg width&#x3D;&quot;312pt&quot; height&#x3D;&quot;260pt&quot;
 viewBox&#x3D;&quot;0.00 0.00 311.67 260.00&quot; xmlns&#x3D;&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; xmlns:xlink&#x3D;&quot;http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink&quot;&gt;
&lt;g id&#x3D;&quot;graph0&quot; class&#x3D;&quot;graph&quot; transform&#x3D;&quot;scale(1 1) rotate(0) translate(4 256)&quot;&gt;
&lt;polygon class&#x3D;&quot;diagram-transparent-white&quot; points&#x3D;&quot;-4,4 -4,-256 307.67,-256 307.67,4 -4,4&quot;/&gt;
&lt;g id&#x3D;&quot;node1&quot; class&#x3D;&quot;node&quot;&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Compile Graphviz to WebAssembly&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;ellipse class&#x3D;&quot;diagram-black-none&quot; cx&#x3D;&quot;151.84&quot; cy&#x3D;&quot;-234&quot; rx&#x3D;&quot;151.67&quot; ry&#x3D;&quot;18&quot;/&gt;
&lt;text text-anchor&#x3D;&quot;middle&quot; x&#x3D;&quot;151.84&quot; y&#x3D;&quot;-229.8&quot; font-size&#x3D;&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;Compile Graphviz to WebAssembly&lt;/text&gt;
&lt;/g&gt;
&lt;g id&#x3D;&quot;node2&quot; class&#x3D;&quot;node&quot;&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Generate diagrams at build time&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;ellipse class&#x3D;&quot;diagram-black-none&quot; cx&#x3D;&quot;151.84&quot; cy&#x3D;&quot;-162&quot; rx&#x3D;&quot;134.85&quot; ry&#x3D;&quot;18&quot;/&gt;
&lt;text text-anchor&#x3D;&quot;middle&quot; x&#x3D;&quot;151.84&quot; y&#x3D;&quot;-157.8&quot; font-size&#x3D;&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;Generate diagrams at build time&lt;/text&gt;
&lt;/g&gt;
&lt;g id&#x3D;&quot;edge1&quot; class&#x3D;&quot;edge&quot;&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Compile Graphviz to WebAssembly&amp;#45;&amp;gt;Generate diagrams at build time&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;path class&#x3D;&quot;diagram-black-none&quot; d&#x3D;&quot;M151.84,-215.7C151.84,-207.98 151.84,-198.71 151.84,-190.11&quot;/&gt;
&lt;polygon class&#x3D;&quot;diagram-black-black&quot; points&#x3D;&quot;155.34,-190.1 151.84,-180.1 148.34,-190.1 155.34,-190.1&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/g&gt;
&lt;g id&#x3D;&quot;node3&quot; class&#x3D;&quot;node&quot;&gt;
&lt;title&gt;???&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;ellipse class&#x3D;&quot;diagram-black-none&quot; cx&#x3D;&quot;151.84&quot; cy&#x3D;&quot;-90&quot; rx&#x3D;&quot;27&quot; ry&#x3D;&quot;18&quot;/&gt;
&lt;text text-anchor&#x3D;&quot;middle&quot; x&#x3D;&quot;151.84&quot; y&#x3D;&quot;-85.8&quot; font-size&#x3D;&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;???&lt;/text&gt;
&lt;/g&gt;
&lt;g id&#x3D;&quot;edge2&quot; class&#x3D;&quot;edge&quot;&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Generate diagrams at build time&amp;#45;&amp;gt;???&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;path class&#x3D;&quot;diagram-black-none&quot; d&#x3D;&quot;M151.84,-143.7C151.84,-135.98 151.84,-126.71 151.84,-118.11&quot;/&gt;
&lt;polygon class&#x3D;&quot;diagram-black-black&quot; points&#x3D;&quot;155.34,-118.1 151.84,-108.1 148.34,-118.1 155.34,-118.1&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/g&gt;
&lt;g id&#x3D;&quot;node4&quot; class&#x3D;&quot;node&quot;&gt;
&lt;title&gt;Profit!&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;ellipse class&#x3D;&quot;diagram-black-none&quot; cx&#x3D;&quot;151.84&quot; cy&#x3D;&quot;-18&quot; rx&#x3D;&quot;36.49&quot; ry&#x3D;&quot;18&quot;/&gt;
&lt;text text-anchor&#x3D;&quot;middle&quot; x&#x3D;&quot;151.84&quot; y&#x3D;&quot;-13.8&quot; font-size&#x3D;&quot;14.00&quot;&gt;Profit!&lt;/text&gt;
&lt;/g&gt;
&lt;g id&#x3D;&quot;edge3&quot; class&#x3D;&quot;edge&quot;&gt;
&lt;title&gt;???&amp;#45;&amp;gt;Profit!&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;path class&#x3D;&quot;diagram-black-none&quot; d&#x3D;&quot;M151.84,-71.7C151.84,-63.98 151.84,-54.71 151.84,-46.11&quot;/&gt;
&lt;polygon class&#x3D;&quot;diagram-black-black&quot; points&#x3D;&quot;155.34,-46.1 151.84,-36.1 148.34,-46.1 155.34,-46.1&quot;/&gt;
&lt;/g&gt;
&lt;/g&gt;
&lt;/svg&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That diagram was generated using the following Markdown:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-md&quot;&gt;&#x60;&#x60;&#x60;dot2svg
digraph {
    &amp;quot;Compile Graphviz to WebAssembly&amp;quot; -&amp;gt; &amp;quot;Generate diagrams at build time&amp;quot; -&amp;gt; &amp;quot;???&amp;quot; -&amp;gt; &amp;quot;Profit!&amp;quot;;
}
&#x60;&#x60;&#x60;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;extending-the-marked-renderer&quot;&gt;Extending the Marked renderer&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As shown in the example near the top of this post, my plan is to piggyback on Markdown code blocks, using a special language tag &lt;code&gt;dot2svg&lt;/code&gt;. For all other code blocks (and on error), I simply defer to the default code block rendering function:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;// Generate diagrams with dot2svg
const baseCodeRenderer &#x3D; markdownRenderer.code;
const dotConverter &#x3D; await createDOTToSVGAsync();
markdownRenderer.code &#x3D; function (code, language, escaped) {
    if (language &#x3D;&#x3D;&#x3D; &amp;quot;dot2svg&amp;quot;) {
        const svg &#x3D; dotConverter.dotToSVG(code);
        if (svg) {
            return svg;
        } else {
            // On error, just treat the code block like normal
            language &#x3D; &amp;quot;&amp;quot;;
        }
    }
    return baseCodeRenderer.call(this, code, language, escaped);
};
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;styling&quot;&gt;Styling&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above rendering code worked (and didn&amp;#39;t break my &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/metalsmith-syntax-highlighting.html&quot;&gt;syntax highlighting&lt;/a&gt;), but there were a few tweaks I had in mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove the &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/xml/#sec-prolog-dtd&quot;&gt;XML prolog and document type declaration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since I&amp;#39;m inlining my SVG in HTML, this information is redundant&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Replace Graphviz&amp;#39;s default styling (annoyingly hard-coded via &lt;code&gt;fill&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;stroke&lt;/code&gt; attributes on each element) with CSS classes&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This allows me to style the graphs using my CSS stylesheet&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In my case, I&amp;#39;m replacing the &lt;code&gt;fill&#x3D;&amp;quot;white&amp;quot; stroke&#x3D;&amp;quot;black&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; attributes with a single CSS class: &lt;code&gt;class&#x3D;&amp;quot;diagram-black-white&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, both of these transformations can be done with regular expression replacements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-javascript&quot;&gt;...
if (svg) {
    // Remove XML prolog, since we&amp;#39;re inlining
    // Also convert default styles to CSS classes, for custom styling
    return svg
        .replace(/^.*?&amp;lt;svg /s, &amp;quot;&amp;lt;svg &amp;quot;)
        .replace(/fill&#x3D;&amp;quot;([^&amp;quot;]+)&amp;quot; stroke&#x3D;&amp;quot;([^&amp;quot;]+)&amp;quot;/g, &amp;quot;class&#x3D;\&amp;quot;diagram-$2-$1\&amp;quot;&amp;quot;);
} else {
...
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I can just style everything with CSS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class&#x3D;&quot;language-css&quot;&gt;/* Diagrams */
svg text { fill: #eee; }
.diagram-transparent-white { stroke: none; fill: none; }
ellipse.diagram-black-none { stroke: #ccc; fill: #444; }
.diagram-black-none { stroke: #999; fill:none; }
.diagram-black-black { stroke: #999; fill: #333; }
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h1 id&#x3D;&quot;thats-it&quot;&gt;That&amp;#39;s it!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, this entire integration went smoothly, and only took an hour or so. It remains to be seen how useful these diagrams will be, but at least now if I ever feel the need to insert a superfluous diagram, the functionality will be there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For reference, all of the code used to generate this site (along with the content) is in &lt;a href&#x3D;&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/md2blog&quot;&gt;this repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: I&amp;#39;ve removed this feature from my static site generator for the time being because it&amp;#39;s unclear what license covers Graphviz (the web site and source code are not in sync).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>
</feed>
