<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<title>Schemescape</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/</id>
<link rel="self" href="https://log.schemescape.com/feed.xml"/>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/"/>
<author>
<name>Schemescape</name>
</author>
<updated>2025-06-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>

<entry>
<title>luasmith gets link-checking and improved Atom feeds</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/extending-luasmith.html</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/extending-luasmith.html"/>
<updated>2025-06-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<summary type="text">Feature creep has set in for my ~270 KB static site generator, luasmith.</summary>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently, I created &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/luasmith&quot;&gt;luasmith&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/smallest-static-site-generator.html&quot;&gt;a ~270 KB static site generator&lt;/a&gt;, with a focus on being small and simple. Obviously, I am now recklessly stuffing it with features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;bloat&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Bloat&amp;quot;&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initial version of luasmith lacked some functionality I valued from &lt;a href=&quot;https://jaredkrinke.github.io/md2blog/&quot;&gt;md2blog&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Checking for broken internal links (including hashes/fragments/anchors)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Including post content directly within the Atom feed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the latest release of luasmith includes these features, and there&#039;s good news from a bloat perspective:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These additions &lt;strong&gt;only added ~3 KB to the (compressed) size of the release&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generating my blog still takes &amp;lt; 200 ms&lt;/strong&gt;, on an old laptop (though it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; ~20% slower, in relative terms)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-now-how&quot;&gt;Why now? How?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason luasmith didn&#039;t originally include these features, despite their utility, is that they require &lt;strong&gt;additional parsing&lt;/strong&gt; (well... you could maybe hook into the Markdown parser, but, besides tight coupling, it wouldn&#039;t work outside of Markdown). For link-checking, it&#039;s obvious why parsing is required. For Atom feed content, the reason is that most RSS/Atom readers don&#039;t support adjusting relative links using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.w3.org/TR/xmlbase/&quot;&gt;xml:base&lt;/a&gt;, so relative links from e.g. &lt;code&gt;posts/topic/foo.html&lt;/code&gt; won&#039;t work without modification when viewed from &lt;code&gt;posts/feed.xml&lt;/code&gt; (which is in a different directory). (My solution is to rewrite relative links.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rather than pull in some heavyweight parsing library, I decided to roll my own minimal HTML parser/transformer: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/chtml&quot;&gt;chtml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. It&#039;s probably deficient and definitely poorly documented, but it seems to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;lua&quot;&gt;Lua&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again, I&#039;ve found C and Lua to be a comfortable combination. I wasn&#039;t looking forward to writing string manipulation code in C, but I had no need to fear--I just pushed all string manipulation into the somewhat safer world of Lua. Problem &lt;del&gt;solved&lt;/del&gt; avoided!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having said that, &lt;strong&gt;I&#039;m still trying to decide how I &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; feel about Lua&lt;/strong&gt;. On the one hand, I like that I can easily integrate C code, leading to a process where I write performance-critical code in C and everything else in Lua. This combination provides both convenience and performance. &lt;em&gt;But&lt;/em&gt; I am starting to wonder if it would make more sense to just write &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; in a more featureful language and then rely on a JIT to make things fast. Yes, I&#039;m talking about TypeScript/JavaScript and Node.js. &lt;strong&gt;It frustrates me to pull in such a huge engineering effort (V8), just to make my own developer life a bit more convenient&lt;/strong&gt;... but I can see why businesses are constantly making that choice. Of course, I also dislike these businesses&#039; bloated results, so I don&#039;t necessarily &lt;em&gt;agree&lt;/em&gt; with their logic. Like I said: still pondering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-last-biggest-challenge&quot;&gt;The last, biggest challenge&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Annoyingly, I&#039;m still not at the point where I can fully replace md2blog because I like build-time syntax highlighting for code blocks. md2blog uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://highlightjs.org/&quot;&gt;highlight.js&lt;/a&gt; for syntax highlighting, and it was super convenient to integrate with Node and Deno. But luasmith is built on C and Lua instead of JavaScript, so highlight.js doesn&#039;t really have a place to plug in. Embedding QuickJS just for highlight.js would contradict my simplicity goal, so I need a different solution. Sadly, most syntax highlighting solutions seem to be based on JavaScript. Or Rust, which I am also avoiding for this side project, due to complexity. It&#039;s almost certainly misguided, but, &lt;strong&gt;for hobbies, I&#039;d like to stick to a software stack that I feel like I can at least ever have a hope of understanding in its entirety&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe some day I will work up the nerve to integrate &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/tree-sitter/tree-sitter&quot;&gt;Tree-sitter&lt;/a&gt; and a bunch of associated grammars, to add syntax highlighting (bringing luasmith into build-time featuer parity with md2blog), but I&#039;m sure that will massively increase the size and (internal) complexity of luasmith. Or perhaps I can write an optional, external tool that is purpose-built for syntax highlighting. We&#039;ll see...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;addendum-with-actual-bloat&quot;&gt;Addendum, with actual bloat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I learned that Tree-sitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://tree-sitter.github.io/tree-sitter/cli/index.html&quot;&gt;has a command line interface&lt;/a&gt;. Problem solved, right? Let&#039;s install and find out:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt install tree-sitter-cli
Reading package lists... Done
...
The following additional packages will be installed:
  binaryen clang-15 emscripten gyp libcares2 libclang-common-15-dev libclang-cpp15t64 libclang-rt-15-dev libclang1-15t64 libjs-d3 libjs-inherits libllvm15t64 libnode-dev libnode109 lld-15 llvm-15 llvm-15-dev llvm-15-linker-tools
  llvm-15-runtime llvm-15-tools node-abbrev node-acorn node-agent-base node-ansi-regex node-ansi-styles node-aproba node-are-we-there-yet node-balanced-match node-brace-expansion node-busboy node-chownr node-cjs-module-lexer node-clone
  node-color-convert node-color-name node-console-control-strings node-core-util-is node-data-uri-to-buffer node-debug node-defaults node-delegates node-encoding node-fancy-log node-fetch node-fs.realpath node-gauge node-glob
  node-graceful-fs node-gyp node-has-unicode node-https-proxy-agent node-iconv-lite node-inflight node-inherits node-isarray node-isexe node-jsonparse node-lru-cache node-minimatch node-minipass node-mkdirp node-ms node-nopt node-npmlog
  node-once node-osenv node-process-nextick-args node-readable-stream node-rimraf node-safe-buffer node-semver node-set-blocking node-signal-exit node-slice-ansi node-string-decoder node-string-width node-strip-ansi node-tar
  node-time-stamp node-undici node-util-deprecate node-wcwidth.js node-which node-wide-align node-wrappy node-xtend node-yallist nodejs nodejs-doc python3-numpy
...
0 upgraded, 91 newly installed, 0 to remove and 75 not upgraded.
Need to get 228 MB of archives.
After this operation, 1,594 MB of additional disk space will be used.
Do you want to continue? [Y/n] n
Abort.
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That&#039;s nearly 1.6 GB of disk space for a Tree-sitter CLI&lt;/strong&gt;. I&#039;m speechless. I guess it&#039;s written in JavaScript for Node.js, so that explains ~100 MB of it. But why does it need LLVM? Emscripten?? NumPy???&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect this is mostly related to Node.js native modules (and perhaps how they&#039;re packaged on Debian, specifically), but... &lt;strong&gt;I just can&#039;t deal with this level of bloat&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>A 270 KB static site generator based on Markdown and Lua</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/smallest-static-site-generator.html</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/smallest-static-site-generator.html"/>
<updated>2025-04-22T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<summary type="text">Tired of bloat, I made a new static site generator that is 10x faster and 100x smaller than my last effort. And this one runs on NetBSD.</summary>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I unveil my most gratuitous static site generator yet: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/luasmith&quot;&gt;luasmith&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It&#039;s &lt;del&gt;270 KB&lt;/del&gt; 450 KB&lt;/strong&gt; (static binary + templates for this site, gzip compressed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It builds my ~140 page site in &lt;del&gt;150 ms&lt;/del&gt; 300 ms&lt;/strong&gt; (wall clock time, on an 11-year-old old laptop)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It performs acceptably on a 28-year-old laptop, running NetBSD&lt;/strong&gt; (Pentium 166 MHz)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It&#039;s trivial to compile&lt;/strong&gt;, requiring only a C compiler, &lt;code&gt;make&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;show-me-the-code&quot;&gt;Show me the code!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#039;s like &lt;a href=&quot;https://metalsmith.io/&quot;&gt;Metalsmith&lt;/a&gt; in Lua. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/luasmith/blob/main/docs/tutorial.md&quot;&gt;the tutorial&lt;/a&gt; for more, but here&#039;s an example that converts Markdown to HTML and adds the page&#039;s title to the resulting HTML:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lua&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-comment&quot;&gt;-- Minimal HTML template (used below)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;hl-keyword&quot;&gt;local&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;hl-identifier&quot;&gt;outer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;hl-string_longstring&quot;&gt;[[
&amp;lt;html&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;head&amp;gt;&amp;lt;title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;%= title %&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/title&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/head&amp;gt;
  &amp;lt;body&amp;gt;&amp;lt;%- content %&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/body&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/html&amp;gt;
]]&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;hl-comment&quot;&gt;-- Read content/*.md, convert to HTML,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;hl-comment&quot;&gt;-- apply template, write to out/*.html&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;hl-keyword&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;hl-function&quot;&gt;readFromSource&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-string&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;content&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;hl-function&quot;&gt;processMarkdown&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;hl-function&quot;&gt;applyTemplates&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;hl-string&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;%.html$&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;hl-identifier&quot;&gt;outer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;hl-function&quot;&gt;writeToDestination&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-string&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;out&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;hl-operator&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, the world does not need another static site generator--and I don&#039;t expect this SSG to become popular. So how did I end up here?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a word, my motivation was: &lt;strong&gt;simplicity&lt;/strong&gt;. I wanted an SSG that was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple to understand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple to bootstrap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple to maintain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Simple to deploy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;implementation&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#039;s my take on the goals above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;simple-to-understand&quot;&gt;Simple to understand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I wanted the architecture to be simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The build pipeline is just a Lua script (similar to &lt;a href=&quot;https://metalsmith.io/&quot;&gt;Metalsmith&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Page templates are constructed using Lua&lt;/strong&gt; (via &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/leafo/etlua&quot;&gt;etlua&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metadata on items can be specified in frontmatter using Lua (or a subset of YAML)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relative links between Markdown files &amp;quot;just work&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt; and are checked at build time (including links to headings)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of creating a bespoke domain-specific language for defining the structure of a generated site or its templates, you just write some Lua code that glues together a few processing nodes and then supply templates that &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; use Lua (e.g. for iteration).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, I&#039;d describe the architecture as &amp;quot;&lt;strong&gt;Metalsmith in Lua, with zero runtime dependencies&lt;/strong&gt; (beyond libc)&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;simple-to-bootstrap&quot;&gt;Simple to bootstrap&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given my &lt;a href=&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/static-site-generators/../programming-languages/future-proof-languages.html&quot;&gt;musings about future-proof programming languages&lt;/a&gt;, it&#039;s obvious that I&#039;d like to be able to continue to compile and use my software in the future. That is easier said than done! The problem is that identifying languages that will stick around is hard. Twenty years ago, Perl might have been a reasonable choice for an SSG, but today I don&#039;t even remember how to setup a Perl project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://jaredkrinke.github.io/md2blog/&quot;&gt;The best static site generator ever made&lt;/a&gt; is built on TypeScript/JavaScript and &lt;a href=&quot;https://deno.com/&quot;&gt;Deno&lt;/a&gt;. As much as I like Deno, I&#039;m not sure it will be maintained decades down the road. Given that I&#039;ll never know how to get it running on an i586 computer, I have doubts I&#039;d be able to get it running on potential future architectures either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To avoid these headaches, I went with the lowest common denominator: C&lt;/strong&gt;. It&#039;s not convenient, it&#039;s not modern, but C works everywhere and I&#039;m certain C will persist (for better or worse).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside: ideally, I&#039;d be writing as much native code in Rust as possible, to ensure memory safety. Unfortunately, &lt;strong&gt;Rust&#039;s modern approach is at odds with my desire for simplicity&lt;/strong&gt;. The toolchain is huge, the dependency trees are large, and the language is vast. Rust definitely looks like the future of robust low-level software, but &lt;strong&gt;for cozy side projects, I prefer being a simpleton living in the past&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;simple-to-maintain&quot;&gt;Simple to maintain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One frustration I have with the JavaScript ecosystem is that it&#039;s constantly changing. Node, Deno, and Bun do a respectable job of keeping old versions around, but I don&#039;t want to have to worry about breaking changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, C changes very slowly, and previous verisons of Lua are essentially set in stone. Throw in some static linking, and you&#039;ve even got an artifact that should stay usable for a long time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#039;ve also minimized the number of (vendored, compile-time) dependencies involved. Here&#039;s the full list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mity/md4c&quot;&gt;md4c&lt;/a&gt; for converting Markdown to HTML&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lua.org/&quot;&gt;Lua&lt;/a&gt; for metadata, scripting, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/leafo/etlua&quot;&gt;etlua&lt;/a&gt; for templates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update&lt;/strong&gt;: Added in a few more for syntax highlighting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inf.puc-rio.br/~roberto/lpeg/&quot;&gt;LPeg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/orbitalquark/scintillua&quot;&gt;Scintillua&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You&#039;ll note that these libraries are doing all of the heavy lifting&lt;/strong&gt;. I&#039;ve basically only written glue code, an entry point, and some infrastructure. And most of the code I wrote is in Lua (which is much easier to write than C--and fast enough for all but the innermost loops).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;simple-to-deploy&quot;&gt;Simple to deploy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Static binaries are wonderful. &lt;em&gt;Tiny&lt;/em&gt; static binaries are even wonderful-er. &lt;strong&gt;Just copy over a tiny zip file, unzip it, and you&#039;re done&lt;/strong&gt;. Need I say more?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;downsides&quot;&gt;Downsides&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are downsides to the approach I took:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Writing C code is fraught with peril -- fortunately, the hardest parts were mostly already done by the md4c and Lua authors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Syntax highlighting is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; simple -- so I just cut that feature, at least for now (&lt;strong&gt;update&lt;/strong&gt;: syntax highlighting is not supported!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The security model of an SSG that uses Lua scripts for everything is... not ideal -- &lt;strong&gt;only use templates you trust!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I haven&#039;t taken the time to setup a proper development and debugging environment for C and Lua. I need to investiage static analysis and debugging tools for Lua, as well as find a tolerable frontend for GDB. This is where I really miss Emacs+SLIME for Common Lisp or VS Code for TypeScript/Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;future-areas-of-exploration&quot;&gt;Future areas of exploration&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I&#039;ve got a static site generator running on a vintage laptop with NetBSD, where am I headed next? I&#039;m not exactly sure, but some ideas follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;designing-for-the-text-mode-web&quot;&gt;Designing for the text-mode web&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point, I&#039;d like to redesign my site using an even more minimal theme. In fact, &lt;strong&gt;I&#039;d like to optimize my site for text mode browsers&lt;/strong&gt; like &lt;a href=&quot;https://lynx.browser.org/&quot;&gt;lynx&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://w3m.sourceforge.net/&quot;&gt;w3m&lt;/a&gt;. Why? Because I like using w3m and I want my site to be easy to use within w3m. Or maybe it&#039;s because I hate how bloated modern web browsers have become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-simplifying-distribution&quot;&gt;Further simplifying distribution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distributing native code necessarily requires per-platform packages. Or does it? Can I package and release this minimal static site generator as a multi-OS polyglot binary using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jart/cosmopolitan&quot;&gt;Cosmopolitan libc&lt;/a&gt;? Note: sadly, I don&#039;t think 32-bit/i386 is supported for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;simplifying-the-entire-system&quot;&gt;Simplifying the entire system&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#039;d like to see if I can bootstrap my entire web site&#039;s workflow from &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/oasislinux/oasis&quot;&gt;Oasis Linux&lt;/a&gt; (a small, statically linked, Linux-based operating system that is simple, but capable). &lt;strong&gt;Oasis sounds like a modern system that a single person can wrap their head around&lt;/strong&gt; (minus the Linux kernel--though perhaps a simpler kernel could be substitutded...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;blogging-on-vintage-computers&quot;&gt;Blogging on vintage computers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#039;m curious how far back I can go as far as vintage computing and still be able to build a static site. Can I build my SSG on Windows 98? DOS? Amiga? Inquiring minds want to know!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;incremental-builds&quot;&gt;Incremental builds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of old, slow computers, I secretly designed this SSG to support incremental rebuilds to ensure that it runs fast even on old hardware. The only issue with this plan is that &lt;strong&gt;md4c is so fast that I&#039;m not sure it&#039;s worth optimizing the build process&lt;/strong&gt;. I can rebuild my entire site from scratch on a 166 MHz laptop in a few seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating a &lt;em&gt;non-bloated&lt;/em&gt; Markdown-based static site generator has been a bucket list item for me--and now it&#039;s done!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond personal goals, &lt;strong&gt;I found C+Lua to be a comfortable combination for side projects&lt;/strong&gt;. This came as a surprise! Lua isn&#039;t my favorite language to write (though it&#039;s certainly much simpler to wield than C). Having said that, it&#039;s a beautifully simple language that&#039;s easy to integrate. Despite being primarily driven to Lua by my goal of building a small (in binary size) tool, Lua&#039;s minimalist take on a mostly-normal-looking scripting language won me over because I could literally pick it up and be productive within an hour or two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that out of the way, &lt;strong&gt;I should probably attend to hobbies other than static site generator performance art&lt;/strong&gt;. Until next time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/luasmith&quot;&gt;Repository for luasmith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/luasmith/blob/main/docs/tutorial.md&quot;&gt;Tutorial for luasmith&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Did the Google Domains sale to Squarespace open my domain up to phishers?</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/posts/web-development/squarespace-phishing.html</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/posts/web-development/squarespace-phishing.html"/>
<updated>2025-03-14T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<summary type="text">That time I got phishing mail from my own domain.</summary>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;About 5 weeks ago, I randomly checked my spam mail folder and saw a phishing mail &lt;em&gt;sent from my own domain&lt;/em&gt;, schemescape.com. I assumed it was marked as spam because it couldn&#039;t be validated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, &lt;strong&gt;the mail was verified (via &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sender_Policy_Framework&quot;&gt;SPF&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DomainKeys_Identified_Mail&quot;&gt;DKIM&lt;/a&gt;) as being from schemescape.com.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#039;m pretty sure I hadn&#039;t tried to phish myself, so... &lt;strong&gt;what happened?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I originally registered schemescape.com using Google Domains and I set up &lt;em&gt;in-bound&lt;/em&gt; email forwarding, so I could receive mail at my domain (but not send it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On June 15th, 2023, &lt;a href=&quot;https://domains.google/&quot;&gt;Google announced it was selling its Google Domains business to Squarespace&lt;/a&gt;. By July 2024, all domains had been migrated to Squarespace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that context in mind, let&#039;s travel back (forward?) to a few weeks ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;investigation&quot;&gt;Investigation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mailgun&quot;&gt;Mailgun&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To confirm that I didn&#039;t have a &amp;quot;Jekyll and Hyde&amp;quot; self-phishing situation, I checked the email headers and observed that &lt;strong&gt;the mail was sent from a sever I&#039;d never heard of&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;a168.a94b46b0.use4.send.mailgun.net&lt;/code&gt; (198.244.55.168). So what is Mailgun, and how are they sending mail from &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; domain?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mailgun advertises itself as a &amp;quot;transactional email API service for developers&amp;quot;. I think it&#039;s a legitimate business, so I&#039;m assuming some bad actor is abusing their service. I reported the activity to Mailgun, but that only explains that Mailgun is involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;spfdkim&quot;&gt;SPF/DKIM&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#039;t know much about email security, but skimming the Wikipedia articles above indicates:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SPF ensures the sending mail server is authorized to send mail for the domain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DKIM is used to sign (and authenticate) each email from the domain&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poking around my DNS records, &lt;strong&gt;there are two suspicious TXT records&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SPF (on schemescape.com): &lt;code&gt;v=spf1 include:mailgun.org ~all&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DKIM (on k1._domainkey.schemescape.com): &lt;code&gt; k=rsa; p=MIGfMA0GCSqGSIb3DQEBAQUAA4GNADCBiQKBgQDXlrH338T643ulCW/ROaqdFhTlU332Av6qpMN69oMhKJeUgPp9RFHIMnRecVJAdLVDM3R6RpAsgNdB8EGv1Xhu3/vPA83H/KtGv8p6s03oVLhDaN3emmPZRi8WHlyDWM/W9VPE0aOvfWB/3ONXLaQrJOT2 /JUZIAnQ7ocfZl74kwIDAQAB&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where did those come from?&lt;/strong&gt; I certainly never authored those DNS records--I didn&#039;t even know about the &lt;code&gt;_domainkey&lt;/code&gt; part of DKIM! Who created those records?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mailgun-1&quot;&gt;Mailgun&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both records match &lt;a href=&quot;https://help.mailgun.com/hc/en-us/articles/32884702360603-Domain-Verification-Setup-Guide#01GCQE107VSXRWCKSVCHX0XXQQ&quot;&gt;Mailgun&#039;s Domain Verification Setup Guide&lt;/a&gt;, so my domain is setup for Mailgun. &lt;strong&gt;But who set this up?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside: why isn&#039;t Mailgun&#039;s setup unique to each domain?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;squarespace&quot;&gt;Squarespace?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, I wasn&#039;t sure if it was Google or Squarespace that created these records on my behalf. &lt;a href=&quot;https://forum.squarespace.com/topic/296578-squarespace-email-forwarding-defaults-for-ex-google-domains-mailgun/&quot;&gt;A thread on the Squarespace forum&lt;/a&gt; had at least one person noting that their mail forwarding records were modified during the Google Domains -&amp;gt; Squarespace transition, which suggesed it might be Squarespace&#039;s doing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;squarespace-1&quot;&gt;Squarespace!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, DNS records are public, and at least one site has been tracking records over time: &lt;a href=&quot;https://dnshistory.org/&quot;&gt;DNS History (dnshistory.org)&lt;/a&gt;. Looking at their history for my domain, I see that &lt;strong&gt;the SPF record from above was added sometime around May 13th, 2024, right around when Squarespace notified me that my domain had been migrated to their service&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the info above, my best guess is that the Google Domains -&amp;gt; Squarespace transition (or the subsequent Squarespace flow for enabling email forwarding) somehow caused these records to be added, as some sort of (unnecessary, in my case) Mailgun integration. &lt;strong&gt;At that point, a malicious actor just had to claim (&amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;https://help.mailgun.com/hc/en-us/articles/32884702360603-Domain-Verification-Setup-Guide#01GCQE107WHJR205TAGQAERRAG&quot;&gt;verify&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;) my domain on Mailgun, and then they could start phishing&lt;/strong&gt;, using SPF- and DKIM-verified, legitimate-looking mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;squarespace-2&quot;&gt;Squarespace!!!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Annoyingly, &lt;strong&gt;Squarespace seems to &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt; the Mailgun records for any kind of mail forwarding&lt;/strong&gt;. I don&#039;t see an option for in-bound-only forwarding (like I had on Google Domains). So... I don&#039;t see a way to avoid this problem other than creating a Mailgun account and claiming your domain there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;security-response-or-not&quot;&gt;Security response... or not&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I documented my understanding of the issue and reported it to Squarespace, via their Hackerone-based security funnel. Either fortunately (because I misunderstood) or unfortunately (because Squarespace misunderstood), &lt;strong&gt;Squarespace closed my report because it was not a &amp;quot;significant&amp;quot; security issue&lt;/strong&gt;. Obviously, I disagree. I received a &amp;quot;valid&amp;quot; (as far as email security is concerned) phishing mail from my own domain! There&#039;s definitely a problem somewhere!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;My requests for clarification on how email domain hijacking is not a &amp;quot;significant&amp;quot; security issue have, to date, received no response (after roughly 5 weeks)&lt;/strong&gt;. To be fair, I did not attempt to replicate the process outlined above (because everyone I know who used Google Domains had already left Squarespace and hijacking some random person&#039;s domain sounds like actual, illegal hacking).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: I&#039;m not an email security expert (or even any kind of security researcher) and I don&#039;t know how Squarespace and Mailgun are integrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But &lt;strong&gt;I think any Squarespace domain with email forwarding &lt;em&gt;that is not linked to a Mailgun account&lt;/em&gt; could be ripe for phishing&lt;/strong&gt;. I even found that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/gsuite/comments/1fcya1x/google_domains_squarespace_and_email_forwarding/&quot;&gt;someone else came to the same conclusion on Reddit six months ago&lt;/a&gt;. Squarespace assured me there is no problem, but provided no detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, I moved my domain away from Squarespace (to Porkbun). It&#039;s not like I &lt;em&gt;chose&lt;/em&gt; to use Squarespace in the first place--Google chose for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;corrections&quot;&gt;Corrections?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; an email security expert and notice any mistakes in my understanding or logic above, &lt;em&gt;please&lt;/em&gt; email me at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:log@schemescape.com&quot;&gt;log@schemescape.com&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt; I would love both to be wrong (because then there&#039;s not a problem) and to be corrected (so I can learn).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Farewell to a netbook</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/posts/hardware/farewell-to-a-netbook.html</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/posts/hardware/farewell-to-a-netbook.html"/>
<updated>2025-03-04T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<summary type="text">Remembering a forgotten device class that actually aligned with my needs.</summary>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today, I bid farewell to my &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dell_Inspiron_Mini_Series#Dell_Inspiron_Mini_(1018)&quot;&gt;Dell Inspiron Mini 1018&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;netbooks&quot;&gt;Netbooks&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://hackaday.com/2020/06/04/netbooks-the-form-factor-time-forgot/&quot;&gt;Netbooks enjoyed a meteoric rise and fall&lt;/a&gt; in the late 2000s and early 2010s. Basically, they were minimally viable laptops that were maximally affordable. For anyone who wanted a cheapo laptop, they were great! Sure, they were slow, and cramped, and slow. But they were cheap!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, that&#039;s not fair. Netbooks were slower than their contemporaries, but anything clocked over 1 GHz isn&#039;t &amp;quot;slow&amp;quot;. That still should be enough for most reasonable workloads, if not for bloat. But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;personal-history&quot;&gt;Personal history&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#039;t specifically recall when I picked up my netbook, but it was probably in 2010 or 2011. It came with a 1.66 GHz Intel Atom N455 processor, 1 GB of DDR3 RAM, and a spinning hard drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It came preloaded with Windows 7 Starter, which ran... adequately. I used the netbook on the couch and it was pleasant. Just imagine a clunky tablet with a keyboard and no touchscreen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then at some point, I realized that I didn&#039;t really need a laptop, so I loaned it to someone else for work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;end-of-life&quot;&gt;End of life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, I recovered the device and I updated the operating system to Windows 10. Big mistake. Windows 10 performance on this device was abysmal. It took nearly one full minute to open a web browser. It turns out that a 1 GB of RAM is woefully insufficient for Windows 10. Instead of being pleasant, the device became frustrating. Oh well, I still didn&#039;t &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; need a laptop, so I stuck it in a closet and forgot about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That could have been the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;rebirth&quot;&gt;Rebirth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, 2023 rolled around, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/hardware/../programming-languages/minimal-dev-env.html&quot;&gt;I was pining for simpler times&lt;/a&gt;. Why do we keep buying faster computers that mostly perform the same functions as their ancestors? (This was before Windows 11&#039;s TPM 2.0 requirement.) After experimenting with an original Raspberry Pi B (now &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; are slow!) I pulled the netbook back out of my closet and &lt;a href=&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/hardware/../programming-languages/minimal-dev-env-4.html&quot;&gt;set it up as a minimal development environment&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike Windows 10, Linux scales down fairly nicely to moderately old hardware. Using Alpine Linux, I was able to setup a comfortable terminal-only development environment for C. Using the w3m browser, I was able to read &lt;a href=&quot;https://gigamonkeys.com/book/&quot;&gt;Practical Common Lisp&lt;/a&gt; so that I could &lt;a href=&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/hardware/../programming-languages/learning-lisp-in-2023.html&quot;&gt;test out REPL-driven programming in Lisp&lt;/a&gt;. Almost all Common Lisp code I&#039;ve ever written was authored in Emacs on this junky old netbook--and it never felt slow!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-net&quot;&gt;The Net&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, 1 GB of RAM isn&#039;t sufficient for browsing many modern web sites. As much as I enjoy terminal mode browsers, having proportional fonts, colors, and a mouse are convenient. Dillo and NetSurf can help, but many sites require JavaScript, and sandboxing the enormous JavaScript runtime is just no longer possible on a 1 GB device.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite being &lt;em&gt;built&lt;/em&gt; to &amp;quot;surf the net&amp;quot;, most netbooks can&#039;t keep up with the modern web. I&#039;m not happy about this realization, but that doesn&#039;t make it any less true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;last-gasp&quot;&gt;Last gasp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there&#039;s one saving grace, it&#039;s that many netbooks were built with commodity parts that could theoretically be upgraded. In fact, my netbook could accept a solid-state drive and probably at least 4 GB of RAM. In my case, the hard drive and (single) RAM slot could be accessed by removing the plastic shell and the keyboard. Unfortunately, I learned that my particular netbook has a fickle memory slot: it will only accept &amp;quot;full power&amp;quot; DDR3 RAM--multiple &amp;quot;low power&amp;quot; RAM sticks I plugged in failed to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, numerous trial-and-error RAM surgeries appear to have loosened the keyboard&#039;s ribbon connection to the point that it seems unstable. It&#039;s a sad day, but I need to lay this netbook to rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-future&quot;&gt;The future&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are my netbook days over? Maybe not! At some unknown point in the past, I had acquired a second netbook: an &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asus_EeeBook&quot;&gt;Asus EeeBook X205&lt;/a&gt;. It&#039;s not upgradable, but it&#039;s already equipped with 2 GB of RAM. I&#039;m sure the puny 32 GB hard drive will become a problem at some point, but I&#039;m going to throw Linux on and see what happens--it&#039;s not like there&#039;s enough space to install Windows 10 updates anyway!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So there you go: my personal netbook history.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Minimal IRC server from scratch in Python</title>
<id>https://log.schemescape.com/posts/diy/irc-server-in-python.html</id>
<link rel="alternate" href="https://log.schemescape.com/posts/diy/irc-server-in-python.html"/>
<updated>2025-02-17T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
<summary type="text">The obvious alternative to using Discord is to write and host my own IRC server!</summary>
<content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is the story of me prototyping a &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/pirc&quot;&gt;minimal IRC server in Python&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The server is currently running (unencrypted/&lt;code&gt;-notls&lt;/code&gt;) on &lt;code&gt;irc.schemescape.com&lt;/code&gt; port 6667 (make sure to &lt;code&gt;/join #general&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;discord&quot;&gt;Discord&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Discord is the Electron of chat:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It has the features people want&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It just works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(Almost) Everyone uses it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;...and &lt;strong&gt;it&#039;s completely unusable on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/diy/../programming-languages/minimal-dev-env-4.html&quot;&gt;old&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://log.schemescape.com/posts/diy/../programming-languages/minimal-dev-env-3.html&quot;&gt;slow&lt;/a&gt; computers I toy with&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several open source alternatives to Discord, including &lt;a href=&quot;https://revolt.chat/&quot;&gt;Revolt&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://gitter.im/&quot;&gt;Gitter&lt;/a&gt;. Their flagship clients look heavyweight, but &lt;strong&gt;the beauty of open source is that there&#039;s almost always an alternative terminal client&lt;/strong&gt;. I&#039;ll investigate those in time. There&#039;s also a decentralized option, &lt;a href=&quot;https://matrix.org/&quot;&gt;Matrix&lt;/a&gt;, which apparently has more than 100 million users. Uh, wow. &lt;strong&gt;I should probably try Matrix!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I didn&#039;t realize Matrix had so many users at the time, so I decided to instead try a chat protocol that was &lt;em&gt;designed&lt;/em&gt; for old computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;internet-relay-chat&quot;&gt;Internet Relay Chat&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IRC&quot;&gt;Wikipedia says IRC was created in 1988&lt;/a&gt;. I haven&#039;t used IRC much and, when I have, I found it to be unapproachable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;problems-with-irc&quot;&gt;Problems with IRC&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are &lt;strong&gt;commands you have to remember&lt;/strong&gt; (and any typo might send your flawed command line straight into the chat window for all to see)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All IRC servers I&#039;ve used broadcast your hostname when you connect&lt;/strong&gt;, unless you setup an account (&lt;em&gt;this guy uses Comcast!!!&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;With IRC, &lt;strong&gt;you generally only receive messages while online&lt;/strong&gt;, so you have to stay connected (or use a &amp;quot;bouncer&amp;quot;) if you want to actually see responses&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There isn&#039;t a convenient, free iOS app for IRC, so IRC basically doesn&#039;t exist for many people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I feel like most of these limitations could be easily overcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;solving-ircs-problems&quot;&gt;Solving IRC&#039;s problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obvious solutions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have actual UI for commands&lt;/strong&gt;, instead of relying on perfectly-entered text commands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hide hostnames by default&lt;/strong&gt; (at least from non-operators)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Store past messages&lt;/strong&gt; in a sequential database and allow clients to request old messages -- note: this seems ripe for AI scraper abuse, and it would require opt-in protocol changes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build a simple web client, optionally create native phone apps, and, of course, supply a lightweight TUI!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you throw in account management and privacy controls, this could get out of hand quickly. And &lt;strong&gt;Matrix already exists and has probably solved these problems&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;not-solving-ircs-problems&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Not&lt;/em&gt; solving IRC&#039;s problems&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My original motivation for investigating chat apps was to see what it would take to setup my own little chat room. I&#039;m still not convinced I &lt;em&gt;need&lt;/em&gt; a chat room, and I&#039;m almost certain it wouldn&#039;t get much use, so let&#039;s cut some corners:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bridging multiple servers? Who cares!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Encryption and user accounts? Not needed, since it&#039;s just for fun!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tracking and querying old messages? Maybe just cache the last 10!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Instead of building any apps, just reuse existing IRC clients!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Operators? Probably a good idea, but not implemented&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#039;t know if worse is &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt;, but it&#039;s certainly &lt;em&gt;easier&lt;/em&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And thus, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/pirc&quot;&gt;pirc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; was born.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;pirc&quot;&gt;pirc&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/jaredkrinke/pirc&quot;&gt;pirc&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; is basically a learning experiment to see how simple an IRC server can be. &lt;strong&gt;The entire server is in a single ~350 line Python file, with no dependencies beyond the Python standard library&lt;/strong&gt;. The code uses a minimum of abstraction (most of the server is one big &lt;code&gt;match&lt;/code&gt; statement). It is almost certainly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; spec-compliant (since I couldn&#039;t actually determine &lt;em&gt;which&lt;/em&gt; IRC spec to work off of--IRC has evolved organically, for better or worse), but it seems to work with &lt;a href=&quot;https://hexchat.github.io/&quot;&gt;HexChat&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://irssi.org/&quot;&gt;Irssi&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://weechat.org/&quot;&gt;WeeChat&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The code is rough, but should be readable, so I won&#039;t attempt to explain it here. Here are some things I learned along the way:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Python&#039;s &lt;code&gt;socketserver&lt;/code&gt; module doesn&#039;t seem to have a simple way to detect when clients disconnect (so I switched to the &lt;code&gt;selectors&lt;/code&gt; module instead)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Python, &lt;code&gt;textwrap.wrap(&amp;quot;&amp;quot;)&lt;/code&gt; returns &lt;code&gt;[]&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;[&amp;quot;&amp;quot;]&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I still think IRC should &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; broadcast hostnames by default (at least to non-operators)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IRC clients send all commands in CAPITAL letters (e.g. &lt;code&gt;JOIN&lt;/code&gt;), &lt;em&gt;except&lt;/em&gt; the &amp;quot;message of the day&amp;quot; command (&lt;code&gt;motd&lt;/code&gt;), which is sent in lowercase (why!?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To my surprise, private messages and messages sent to channels are both &lt;code&gt;PRIVMSG&lt;/code&gt; commands (just directed to a channel instead of a nickname)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;test-server&quot;&gt;Test server&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A test server is currently running (unencrypted/&lt;code&gt;-notls&lt;/code&gt;) on &lt;code&gt;irc.schemescape.com&lt;/code&gt; port 6667 (make sure to &lt;code&gt;/join #general&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
</entry>
</feed>
